Okay, moving over to CodeWorld.
What we see here is exactly the expression that I built
up on the whiteboard (in the preceding, optional video).
If the syntax tree were almost exactly what I
actually had there… it was that this whole polygon
call was inlined into this expression.
So,
I had this thing is what I drew as a tree on
the whiteboard, and a well-defined expression.
And it draws something similar to
what we started from last week.
Okay, but let me not actually focus
so much on the output picture here
because what I really want to do here is to discuss
a few bits of syntax so that you are prepared
also for your own first CodeWorld
programs for the first exercise tasks.
Okay, so what do we have here?
We have this somehow boilerplate
code that is always there.
So, this is given; importing the library.
And this is basically saying that right now
we are going to draw something but not yet do
an animation.
So, then I would have to change this to another
primitive, but let's not do this at the moment,
and well I want to draw this scene,
and I have this expression for it.
Okay.
And in this case already, I introduced
the name for the subexpression.
And I have this now.
Okay, now this equal sign here is very important.
It's not an assignment statement.
Yes.
So, I started the lectures light this week
with saying that functional programming is
essentially programming without assignment
commands, but actually without any commands.
But importantly, no assignment commands.
So, this shouldn't be seen
as: I have a variable “scene”.
And then we assign something to that variable.
And maybe further down, we would
change this and define something else,
something like this.
And you already see on the
left, there's an error.
And this also probably won't go away.
If I complete this. This doesn't make sense
because we are not assigning stuff to variables,
we are declaring some values, and we can't
have two declarations for the same value.
That would be like in a system of equations
to say x equals five, but x also equals
seven.
That would simply be a mathematical
contradiction. We can't have this.
And so, these are not assignment statements,
they are simply declarations of values.
Okay, that also means that the order of
definitions or declarations shouldn't be important.
So, you already see that I use “triangle” here,
which is defined later further down in the
code, but there is no notion of “later” here
because these are not things that happen in
some order.
They are simply equation definitions.
And if you write down a system of linear
equations, three times x plus five y is 11.
And some other equation, then the order in which
you write down the equations is not important.
What is important is what the
equation, say, about the values.
So, if I change the order here, that's technically
a different program, but it is just as well
defined, and, of course,
computes the same picture.
Okay, because we are not assigning stuff to
variables, we are simply defining values.
Okay, this was one thing to keep in mind.
Then there are some things I
should say about the syntax.
So, in particular, you might wonder what this
actually means that you write circle 0.1.
If I said on the whiteboard that circle
is a function, which takes a number,
shouldn't it somehow be written like this?
That probably looks more
like what you're used to.
Or let me, in a comment, write this, so you
are usually used to mathematical syntax, like
defining a function f of x is,
for example, sine of something.
So, f of x is sine of x.
That's how you would write down a function
definition and an expression involving trigonometric
functions like sine.
In mathematics, well, as the difference in
Haskell, mainly, we don't use as many parentheses
brackets, because applying a function
to a value is simply written as f of x.
We don't have to put the argument in
brackets.
Instead, we simply write f space x and the same
here on the right also to apply sine to something,
you don't have to say sine and in brackets
the x, but simply sine applied to x.
Okay.
And this also applies to functions
that take more than one argument.
So, if you have a function that takes two
arguments, then again, in mathematics, we would
maybe write something like f of x
and y is and then, some definition.
And in Haskell, instead, we simply write without
the brackets and without the comma, f x y.
And then we write down the definition.
Okay.
And that's also why, for example, what I drew
in the syntax tree as the translated call,
with three arguments, so it's not written
here, like 'translated', and then the first
argument and the second
argument and something else.
But instead, it's simply written like here,
"translated", space, the first argument, space,
the second argument, space, the third argument,
and this I have to put in brackets, but not
because translated expects brackets there.
But simply because if I were to write it like
that, then it wouldn't be clear what's the
argument to what, right, and one could think
that the "colored" function is the third argument
to translate it and not
the whole expression here.
So there, I have to use brackets.
But it's many fewer brackets than if I had
written this in the mathematical style.
Let me fill this out here, then I
would have written it like that.
And also the “colored” would be written
like this because it takes two arguments.
Okay.
So, that’s not what we do.
What we do is this.
And actually, once you start submitting solutions
to Autotool, it will also warn you about too
many brackets.
You can't even write this because of the commas
which have no place in function application
in Haskell.
But even if you write something without the
commas and try to add more brackets here,
because you feel safer, like adding brackets
around all arguments, then Autotool will tell
you that these brackets are superfluous.
And you are advised to actually make the
suggested changes, so that your programs look
like a program in Haskell usually looks.
Okay, that was some simple syntax remarks.
I already talked about the order
of definitions being unimportant.
And this, of course, becomes more and more
relevant if we introduce further names.
So, for example, I might want, in the spirit
of my earlier comments in the slides, and
on the whiteboard, also introduce names for
further subexpressions where I could say: this
colored red triangle is also something that
I'm interested in maybe reusing, let me say,
this red form should also be given
a name.
And then I could, for example, say, well, I
actually move this out of the above expression
and give it a name.
And then I use this name here.
Okay, so what I did here in this line was that
I also said that this should be a picture.
Actually, I wouldn't have to do this.
Because Haskell does type inference, so even
if I throw away all of these type notations,
Haskell still knows that this is a picture,
even though I haven't written it down here.
Okay.
And if I do something stupid, if I say something
like redForm is simply “red”, then this would
be a type error.
All right.
So, it works out that well, it should be a
“Picture”, but it is just “Color”. It doesn't make
sense
even without any annotations, and if I
give a correct definition, then it works.
Okay, and if I run this, then I get the
same picture, but simply with renamed stuff.
Names for subexpressions.
I didn't change anything about
the values that I compute.
And again, the order in which things are
defined here is completely irrelevant.
If the values are defined,
then that is fine.
Okay, what can I do if I have introduced
the name? Of course, this allows me to reuse
definitions. So for example, I could say in
addition to these two forms, I want to have
another form, so I use this binary operator,
it can also be applied to several arguments,
like a plus. You can write a + b + c,
even though plus is a binary operator.
It's associative.
So, you can write a sequence of additions.
And the same is true for this
operator for combining pictures.
For example, I could say I want to combine
another red form or the same red form, but
now not in this moved form, but actually,
just as it is, and then what will I get?
Well, I expect to see another
triangle here at the origin.
Okay.
And of course, I can also rotate it, for
example, I can say, well, let me rotate this.
So, we know that this would be in radians.
So, let me take half of the number pi.
And what will happen?
I get this picture.
And of course, I haven't really moved
or rotated that red form, right?
It's not like there's a rotated
version of the red form,
and now somehow, this red form is also rotated.
Of course not.
That would not be in the spirit
of mathematical expressions.
That would be like applying an action
and an effect of moving this red form.
But that's not what's happening.
Red form is just this red triangle.
And then I use it here for some
value, and here for something else.
And it's not just because I did this rotation
after the translation, in some sense.
So, this is not about timewise sequencing.
Even if I do it like this, I simply say, first,
I combined things in this way, then this doesn't
mean that now the red form is rotated,
and then if I use it again, then
somehow it's always rotated.
No, that's not the case.
The outcome here will be the exact same picture,
because there is a red triangle, and I use
it here, and rotate it and use the result.
And I use the red form again, and move it.
And then I use this resulting
value as part of my overall scene.
Okay, so this was something
that I wanted to show.
And then I also already wanted to show that
you don't have to have these definitions on
the top level.
So, you don't have to introduce a new name,
or name your subexpressions in the scope of
the complete module. That would be unfortunate,
because then maybe you have very many of these
definitions that are not all
really related to each other.
So, for example, you might want to say, well,
actually, I need this red form only in the
context of this scene
definition, but not elsewhere.
So, you might want to say, well, I want to
use this here, and locally in a sense, and
then what you could do is something like this,
you can say, like mathematics, I want to compute
2 times y where y is x plus one, for example.
So, you can say I want to compute this expression.
In there, I want to use this value name “redForm”,
and I move this definition
locally into this scope.
Then it's again, well-defined, and computes the
same picture, of course. I have simply expressed
this in a different way.
And now I don't have redForm as a global
value that can be used anywhere else.
So, it's now really defined locally
for this “scene” definition.
So, this allows us to group things together.
Maybe that's not so important in your first
exercise tasks, but later, it is a useful
technique to organize your code to
have local definitions in this way.
Okay.
I think that was all the syntax and
features that I wanted to show right now.